OK,
welcome back to 6 .006. We're going to have this problem session. We're doing a
quiz to review. We're in a much bigger room today, so I have a little bit more board
space.
So I just want to go through what's
going to be covered on the exam.
First off, the scope.
Now, quiz one material will be fair game for this quiz, but it's not something that's
going to be explicitly emphasized or anything like that. You should know that when
we're storing graph data structures that they can achieve certain running time bounds
and that kind of thing. But we're really going to be concentrating on graphs. The
six lectures that we've had on graphs, the two on unweighted graph algorithms and
the four that we had on weighted graph algorithms, they covered the material that was
covered in the two problem
sets, problem set five and problem set six.
Now, usually this material covers three problem sets worth of material. This term,
it's covering two problem sets worth of material. So just keep that in mind when
you're studying and you
want to go look back on previous material.
In general, there's lots of graph problems that we've talked about how to solve.
There's really a small number of graph algorithms, but they can solve a lot of different
problems.
And so we saw two algorithms to solve the graph reachability
problem, single source. What is reachable from me?
And I can only search a connected component of my graph from me. And the connected
component from me is actually upper bounded asymptotically by the number of edges in
my graph because
a spanning tree of my component
has at least or has v plus 1 edges.
And so the number of vertices I can reach is upper bounded
by the number of edges in my graph, asymptotically anyway.
Then we talked about exploring an entire graph, even if it's disconnected, not
necessarily from a source, just touching every vertex in a graph. Of course, we can just
touch every vertex in a graph. I can look at the adjacency representation of my graph
and just go through it. But this is really we're trying to explore the whole graph,
maybe count how many things are reachable from each other in the graph. And this is
what we talked about exploring a graph and counting the size of connected components
in a graph in an unweighted graph. And we could do this via full BFS or full BFS.
It's basically putting a loop around one of these graph reachability algorithms to
explore an entire graph by exploring component by component. And when I'm done with
a component, I find a vertex I haven't reached yet before and explore it again. And
that still gets linear time in the graph v
plus e.
Then we had special types of graphs, directed graphs, directed acyclic graphs that
we could use. We proved this property if we ran DFS, full DFS on that graph. We could
actually get topological sort of that graph, basically an ordering of the vertices
in the graph such that all edges go in one direction with respect to that ordering,
like all
forward in that ordering.
And we could actually use that to detect cycles in a directed graph by just looking
at the topological sort order and seeing if look at the finishing time, the reverse
finishing time order of DFS, and just checking to see whether it was a topological
sort order, because any back edge there would correspond to a cycle in our graph,
because the proposition was that if our graph was acyclic,
doing this procedure would give us a topological order.
Then we had an algorithm, Bellman -Ford, that was able to detect and find negative
weight cycles in our graph in the way that we've presented it in lecture. But
normally, we concentrated on these two problems, single source
shortest paths and some a little bit all pair shortest paths.
First in the unweighted context, and then in the
weighted context for the majority of the lectures.
So let's move on to what those single
source shortest paths algorithms were.
We
had, to me, increasing in generality here.
And BFS already solves unweighted shortest paths in linear time. In
the unweighted context, that's all good. But for weighted graphs,
regardless of the weights, if we had this very strong property on the graph that the
graph didn't have any directed cycles, then we could get this in linear time via DAG
relaxation.
And then for general graphs, we had these increasing or decreasing restrictions on
the weights. First, we had the restriction was that they were unweighted, and that's
the BFS constraint,
or that they're non -negative. That's the Dijkstra constraint. And if we have no
constraints, that gives us Bellman -Ford. And they increase in time. In general, you
want to choose an algorithm
that's higher on this list. But sometimes,
the algorithms higher on this list don't apply. If on a quiz, you come to a graph,
for which it's not a DAG, but you use DAG relaxation, that's no longer a correct
algorithm. And so you're going to get fewer points than if you happen to use an
inefficient algorithm that is correct. So whenever I saw shortest paths, I used Bellman
-Ford.
It's the slowest thing.
That's probably going to be a correct algorithm. It's not necessarily going to be
the most efficient algorithm. But you'll get more points because it is a correct
algorithm. Then if you apply a faster algorithm, it doesn't apply to your
problem because it's not going to solve it correctly. Does that make sense?
OK. And then in the last lecture we had, we talked about all -pair shortest paths.
And really, running a single -source shortest path from each vertex is pretty good in
most circumstances. We don't know
how to do a lot better for a lot of these.
It gives us, basically, in this last line of our graph restrictions and weight
restrictions, where Bellman -Ford is right there, we can actually get a speedup over V
times Bellman -Ford by
two tricks.
Find if the graph has negative weight cycles. And if it doesn't, then there
exists a reweighting of this graph so that all the weights are non -negative.
But that shortest paths are preserved. And so we can
use Dijkstra V times and get that running time instead.
So that's an overview of the contents that we've covered so far. Just
want to go, just brief overview of what these algorithms actually do.
DAG relaxation, finds a topological order of the thing using DFS, looking at the
reverse order of the finishing times. Prove that that's a reverse topological order.
And then we relax edges forward in that order because we know that we'll have found
shortest path distance to everything before us before. And we use that invariant to
prove that this constructs it in
linear time.
BFS explores things in levels,
increasing in the number of edges as we go out. And I just
process all of the ones in the same level at the same time.
And Dijkstra generalizes this notion by saying, well, I don't know all of the things
that are in the same level, per se, as I'm going. But I can, using a clever use of a
data structure, find the next one I should process in kind of a DAG topological
relaxation order to find shortest paths when the weights are non -negative. Because in
some sense, I know that once I've reached things from a short distance, I will never
have to update their distance again. That's kind of the invariant that we're having
with Dijkstra. And then Bellman -Ford essentially duplicates our graph so that each
node corresponds to reaching a vertex using, at most, a certain number of edges.
And then that duplicated graph is DAG. And
we can run DAG relaxation.
So that's the basic idea
of all these algorithms.
When I approach problems
on a quiz,
there's a couple of things to keep in mind. There's kind of two things that
we have to worry about when you're looking at a graph problem in this class.
The first thing is, I might not see a graph in my problem. I mean, on quiz two,
you know that there's going to be a graph in your problem, because we covered graph
algorithms on this
quiz. But in general,
some of the word problems you've been seeing on your problem sets, there's no
graph defined for you. They give you an array of things or a set of things or some
connections between some things. And that
might be a graph that you want to make.
But kind of defining a graph is an important aspect of that problem solving that is
not necessarily something that we've covered in lecture. We've not emphasized that in
lecture so much. But it's something that you've had to do on your
problem sets, and it's something that will appear on the quiz.
And part of this is a modeling context. Can you look at
a real world situation, or maybe not so real world, but
non -mathematical context?
And you're trying to abstractify, put it in the language of this class, the mathematics
of this class, make a graph, so that solving one of the problems that you know
how to solve can adequately solve the word problem that we gave you. This is a
modeling part. So I always suggest when you see a word problem on quiz two or on your
problem set, it's that
see if you can state cleanly an abstract problem that if you knew the answer to that
abstract problem, you could easily solve your word problem, can make it a little
easier to decouple the complexity of the word problem.
Then you don't have to think about, I don't know,
various strange characters we come up with
in weird contexts and their weird conditions.
If you can map that to just a graph with certain properties and solving an abstract
problem on that graph, that might be easier for you to think about and apply the
material in this class, so you don't have to worry about, oh, do I have to
remember that roads are connected to five other things, or do I have to remember?
Maybe you're given as the input a sparse graph or something like that.
That's a little easier to think about when applying this material.
But putting your problem into a finding a shortest path problem or finding a cycle
or finding a topological sort or connected components or a negative weight cycle or
any of these kinds of things
can make it easier for you to think about.
It's not like fundamental material in this
class that
we need to lecture on, but it is really important for you when you're out in
the real world looking at problems to be able to make that transformation from a
non -mathematical context to a mathematical. I like to think of this as a modeling
part of the problem. But in general, once you've got that nice abstract problem,
then in general, you might have a graph, but it might not be the only graph you want
when you're solving this problem. That might be the input graph that you have. But
in general, a lot of the tricks of this thing is not modifying the algorithms that
we gave you. If you find yourself trying to modify the algorithms we gave you that we
spent entire lectures on proving their correctness and things like that, that's
maybe not something you want to be doing on an exam because then you're going to be
writing pages of derivation and proof that
the algorithms work.
This unit in particular is much more on the let's reduce to
some very powerful black box that we showed you how it works.
And so because that's the framework here, the way in which we introduce complexity
into problems is to make the graph non -obvious on the thing that you're supposed to
apply. And so the graph that we give you as the input may be different than the graph
that you'll want to use to solve the problem. And here are some strategies that you
can use
to modify a graph. If you want to store state as you're traversing this graph, you
can expand the number of vertices in your graph to keep track of what state I'm in. I
can have a different vertex for every
possible state I could be at that vertex.
In your problem session, you had this guy who's drinking when he got to bars or every
third time. And you need to remember how many times it's been since I've been to a
bar or I had a drunk at a bar. And so you can duplicate
the vertices to be able to store that information.
Another thing, if you need to search from multiple locations at the
same time or search two multiple locations at the same time, you
can simulate that without having to run an algorithm many times. You can simulate
that by adding an auxiliary node, an extra node in your graph with edges to those
sources or to those sinks
and run a single source shortest path algorithm from that super node, sometimes
we call it, to get better performance. It's kind of an efficiency. We're adding
efficiency by changing our graph to fit the
algorithms that we know how to solve efficiently.
And then the last thing, maybe it helps to preprocess the graph in some way. Some
edges in the graph that we gave you might be forbidden or may need to be traversed in
one direction rather than the other, even though the problem
statement seems like they should be traversable in either direction.
And doing this preprocessing of the graph could mean that you break up your graph
into your connected graph into a set of disconnected components that you need to find
or makes a cyclic graph acyclic or prunes part of the graph that you don't want to
explore. I never want to touch on my way to get to a location. And so these are all
really common strategies that we
have,
duplicating graph, adding auxiliary vertices or edges to the graph. I don't know the
context in which we add edges. It's an interesting question. And then preprocessing,
kind of filtering out the graph or transforming it in some way to
give it properties that will allow us to solve the problem better.
So any questions about the problem solving strategies that we have or the kind of
baseline content of this class? This is kind of an overview of the lecture type
material where we're not necessarily
applying this material in lecture.
The purpose of this quiz review session will be on applying this
material to some quiz from a previous term, some of those problems.
So yeah, you have a question? What are some common ways that people lose points when
they write down? What are some common ways people lose points? That's a great thing.
I'll add it to the notes when we
post.
So common things that people lose points
in this unit when they're solving problems.
So you have a super problem, and you don't
define a graph.
It's as easy as that. You start solving, assuming that we know what graph you're
talking about, when the implicit graph in the problem may or may not be correct, but
there's no graph defined in the problem. So you need to define a graph in the
problem. So that's the first thing. The second thing is, a lot of times, it's really
useful, just as a strategy, when you construct that
graph, tell us how many vertices and edges are in it.
Tell us if it's acyclic.
Tell us what the weights are on each edge. If you don't tell us these things, it's
really hard for us to base, to judge your application of algorithms based on that
graph. Because if there's redundancy there, even if you define, for every vertex in
my original graph, I have 10 vertices or blah, blah, blah, and maybe you're adding a
super node or all these things, it can be difficult for us to follow how many things
are. So you do that bookkeeping for us. And then the others are going to be a lot
happier.
So common mistakes,
not defining a graph,
not specifying your graph
completely. And then not,
I would also suggest that instead of just applying an algorithm to a graph,
that you clearly state the problem you're solving on the graph first.
I want to solve this problem. Because we've given you a number of ways to solve
that. Problem on the graph. And if you happen to choose the wrong algorithm,
then maybe that's like
separating off the problem from your implementation of how you solve that problem can
maybe help you get some points for stating the problem you're solving, even if you
choose the wrong or an inefficient way to solve it. So that can really
help decouple some of the things that we're going to give points
on in this class. So usually what we're breaking up a
graph rubric on grading in, did you describe a graph?
Did you modify it in a way
that's going to help you solve the problem?
Did you identify a problem that you need to solve on this thing? Did
you use a correct algorithm to solve it? Did you analyze the runtime?
Usually involves,
is the size
of my graph not too large?
And what is the running time based on that
graph?
And then argument of correctness in this unit is basically like, I constructed a
graph that has properties so that shortest paths in this new graph correspond to
whatever it is that I want in the original problem. Some statement that links the
problem you're solving in your problem statement to the problem you're solving on your
graph, that's a really good statement to have to bring together correctness. But aside
from that statement, you're mostly relying on the correctness of the algorithm, so
you don't need to do much on the correctness side. But forgetting to analyze runtime
is a big thing. OK, so those are a bunch of tips. I'm going to add them to the end
of this slide after the lecture.
Great question. Any other questions?
All right, let's
get to solving problems.
All right,
so these problems that we're
going to solve are from Spring 18, quiz 2,
slightly modified.
But we're just going to go through them one at a time. So the first problem we have,
we have an image of black and white squares. So this is like a pixel grid. You think
of
it as a bitmap on your computer.
And what we say
is each white pixel is contained in a blob.
But what is
a blob? I don't know.
OK, I'm kind of giving you an implicit definition of what a blob is. Two white pixels
are in the same blob if they share an edge of the grid. OK, so this kind of tells
me this graph has an edge if these pixels are adjacent and they're both white. That's
what it means. But an interesting part about that definition is that it kind of is
transitive.
It shares
an edge with a white pixel A that shares a,
let's start writing things on the board,
shall we, instead of me just talking at you.
We have kind
of a pixel grid here.
And I don't know how to do this with a chalkboard because it's
white versus black. I guess I have to color in the white things.
These are all white.
All right, so these guys are in the same blob because
they share an edge. These guys are in the same blob. But
because they share an edge in the pixel grid, these guys are also in the same blob
because if these are in the same blob and these are in the same blob, there's a
transitivity argument here. This guy needs to be in the same blob
as that guy. And then it says that black pixels are not in any blob.
So I'm given an n by m array. I never remember which one comes first. But
we have dimensions of this thing is n by m. So we have n times m pixels.
And so we're describing essentially a linear time algorithm to
compute the number of blobs in the image. Why do I say linear time?
It's because for every pixel in my grid, I needed to give you a specification of
whether that was white or black. So if I naively gave you the input of this algorithm
with a word per one of these pixels, that would be the
input size of my. And so even though this looks quadratic,
the actual input size
is what we define as linear. And so we're looking for a linear time algorithm to
count the number of blobs in the image. OK, so this is a little under -specified as a
problem, I admit.
I hate to admit that I was involved in this class at that
time. But the idea here is if these are share an edge,
then everything, the observation here is if I just draw this picture, I notice that
anything kind of that's reachable through white -white connections is going to be in
the same blob. So this is a blob, and this is a blob, and this is a blob, and this
is a blob. But there's no path here. This black part is not part of a blob. Now,
actually, there's nothing in this specification that says
that we couldn't have these things be in the same blob.
So that's a little confusing, maybe a source of error. This is a source
of error that I had when reading this problem after a couple of years.
But when you are looking at a problem, if everything could just be in the
same blob, then you just return 1, and this problem is not so interesting.
So the right way to interpret this problem, I mean,
I would not need n times m time. I could just say 1.
So in some sense, I'd like there to be something interesting in this problem. And
having these things that are not reachable from each other be different blobs is kind
of the more algorithmically interesting
thing to have. And so what is this then?
A pixel grid, there's adjacencies. There's connections between pixels. But in particular,
I really only care about the connections between white pixels. Hard to draw on
here.
But this
component has a graph that looks like this.
This component is a single vertex. This one's an edge here. And here's a singleton
there. And if we were to construct this graph, we would have an unweighted graph such
that the number of blobs in my image would be the number of connected components in
this graph. See how I'm relating the thing that they're asking for in the problem to
a
property of a graph that I'm constructing?
So that's really the key part of argument of correctness that we're looking for is
for you to make some kind of statement connecting the two. Otherwise, you're just
constructing a graph, and I have
no idea what you're doing to that graph.
It's about communication to us.
So how do I construct this graph? Well,
I can just loop through all of the pixels,
look at its four neighbors,
at most four. And if those
things are both white, then I add an edge.
We're going to essentially have a graph. We're going to construct a graph.
I told you to do this. OK. So what is this? V here, then V is a vertex
for each white pixel.
And I can just, I mean, from the beginning, I can just walk through all the things,
find all the white vertices. Maybe I identify them uniquely by their x, y coordinates
in this.
In this grid, that's fine.
So now I have all the vertices, and now I want to see
what the edges are. I can loop through the pixels again
and just look at its four possible adjacencies, see if any of them
are white, stick that edge in this set. So edge is any two white
pixels that
share an edge.
So I can construct both of these things in this in order n times m, because there's
at most that many vertices. I just loop through them. And the edges, for each pixel,
I'm only checking a constant number of things, and I'm adding them to a set. So the
number of edges, the size of the number of vertices in my graph is at most n times m.
And the number of edges is at
most n times m times 4. It's upper bounded by that, because that's the number of
adjacencies I have in the graph. You can probably get a better bound in terms of the
number of vertices. It can be at most v times 4. But that's a little stronger. It
doesn't really matter. We're trying to get within the order n times m time bound. So
anything's fine here. So that's the graph we construct. And then we can run full BFS
or full DFS. We have identified a graph. We've identified that we want to count the
number of
connected components in my graph.
So idea,
count
connected components.
And then, for example, using full BFS or full DFS. I wouldn't want you to write both
of these algorithms there. But when we write up our solutions, we want them to cover
the space of student solutions. And so we will usually mention it. You only have to
mention one of them. And because these run in linear time, this also runs in n times
m. So all of these things are n times m, and we're golden. Any questions on this
question? Yeah? If I were writing down my proof of correctness and my proof of
efficiency, what sort of thing would you be looking for to make sure? JASON
KURIYAMA - Right. So when I'm writing down, I've described to you the algorithm.
The question is, what kinds of things do I need to write down when I'm proving
or when I'm arguing running time of my algorithm and I'm arguing correctness?
For running time, mostly just check out the
size of your graph.
State to me what the size of your graph is here. In this case, it's order n times m.
And then I state what the running time is of the algorithm that I have is applied to
that. And so because full BFS runs in O of
v plus e time,
it's useful to actually write this down, even though it's not in the terms of our
original problem variables. It's useful to write this down so that if I mess up when
plugging these variables in,
that
you're showing your steps. And so if you mess up arithmetically, then we can still
give you points. But because the number of vertices in the graph is n times m, the
number of edges is n times m, I add them together. It's still order n times m. And
that would be sufficient for an argument of running time. And then as I was saying for
correctness,
most of the correctness of this algorithm is relying on the fact that this thing counts
connected components correctly in my graph. The key observation on a word problem
that I
made, or even a graph transformation problem, is that the property
that you're wanting of the original graph or the original problem
corresponds to the thing you're solving in a new graph that you've made. And so
here, an argument of correctness that I would be looking for that we might allow some
weaker statements is that the number of blobs in the image corresponds
to the number of connected components in this graph that I made.
That's really all it needs. But I would
like a connection between those values.
Now, why would you be constructing this graph and finding
connected components if that wasn't what your thought was?
I don't know. But it's good when you're communicating to make sure that that's
abundantly clear that that's why this is. I mean, you should be able to argue why these
things are
connected component. You could say something like, because
anything reachable is in the same blob or something like that.
OK, so that's problem one.
We got these
nice mechanical boards.
So that's
problem one. Problem two is a little funky.
It's been reworded a little bit from Spring 18 so that I could point out some other
features of this graph. We're given a connected. So connected is in bold. So that
might be an important property of our graph that we're
trying to communicate to you. A connected undirected graph
with strictly positive edge weights. So you're mapping to the positive integers where
E is the same size as V. So the size of E is the same as the size of V. So I have
the same
number of edges as I have vertices.
We're trying to find a order V time algorithm to determine a
path from some vertex s to some vertex t with minimum weight.
So what's
the first thing I notice? I notice that on
this thing, I've got a graph.
So problem two,
we've got a graph.
It's undirected.
It's connected.
It has this weird property that V equals E
or E equals V.
And weights are positive.
OK.
And we're asking for a single pair shortest paths.
We want a path, the shortest path, a shortest path,
between two vertices.
Now, if we just were given this graph and we want to solve this problem, a very
easy way to do that would be to just say, let's run Dijkstra on the graph. This is a
graph. It has only
positive edge weights.
Run Dijkstra
on this graph. How long does Dijkstra take
on this graph? Idea one.
Run Dijkstra.
What's the problem with this?
We're in
the context of non -negative edge weights.
We can find single source shortest paths from s to everything else in the graph
using Dijkstra. It applies. It's a correct algorithm. What's the difficulty with this
algorithm?
Too slow. JASON
KU - Too slow, right?
That algorithm would run
in O of V log V plus E. And in this case, these are the same. This one is
asymptotically smaller than this one. It runs in V log V. So we're a little off.
We're off by a logarithmic factor in our running
time. But this would at least be a correct algorithm.
Whenever you approach a problem on the exam and you see a really stupid polynomial
algorithm that still solves your problem correctly, you might as well write that down
in a line. It doesn't hurt you that much to just write that
down because it's possible it would give you points for that.
But on
your exam, notice why it is not sufficient.
Notice that this is V. Notice that this is not the running time
bound we're looking for. We've got to exploit something different.
Now, this is a weighted context. We have weighted paths. It doesn't seem to be in
one of the conditions that we can get a linear time weighted single source shortest
path algorithm.
In particular, using BFS, we saw a transformation where as long as the sum of your
weights was linear in the common tutorial size of your graph, we could use BFS
by making each edge a bunch of undirected edges. We don't
have that in this context. And this graph is undirected.
So it definitely contains
cycles. So we can't use DAG shortest paths.
So how the heck can we do this?
Well, what does this graph look like? Here, I'm
going to take a look at this condition, V equals E.
So what does this graph look like? It's connected and
it's V plus E. Well, how many edges does a tree have?
V minus 1.
So in a sense, a tree is the smallest number
of edges you can have in a connected graph.
So this has one more edge than a tree. So really what this
looks like, what our graph G looks like, is some kind of tree.
And somewhere, we've got
an extra edge in
this graph.
It's a tree plus an extra edge. That's what
our graph is.
So well, let's take a step back. If I just had a
tree and I had a weighted graph here, undirected,
and the weights are all
positive,
if any of the weights were negative, how could I solve this problem? Well, every edge
is reachable from every vertex. I can just go to that edge and traverse a negative
weight back and forth.
And my shortest pathway would
be infinite for all our vertices. That's not the case we have here. We have positive
edge weights only, which means shortest paths are simple. And actually, there's only
one simple path between any pair
of vertices in a tree.
Basically, there's one thing I can do. And in fact, if I took, if
this was S and this was T, T, that's an X. What am I doing? OK, T,
if I just ran any unweighted shortest, I mean, reachability algorithm, I would
get a tree, a BFS tree or a DFS tree. It would visit vertices in some order. Now,
actually, in a tree,
I have to output
a tree that connects all the vertices.
And that would be this tree.
And so in a sense, the paths that I got from BFS or DFS in this graph would be exactly
shortest paths. I would just have to then go and add up all the path edge weights
along the edges.
Does that make sense?
OK, so BFS or DFS in the unweighted context can give me the shortest path in the
weighted context because there's only one simple path in this graph. But we have a
complication here. That's not the question
that we're asking. We have an extra edge.
Property where there's not just one simple path to T. There could be two simple
paths. I could go this way around the cycle or I could go this way around the cycle.
So that's
a complication. But there's only one cycle.
If T is over here, there's only one
path. So if there is only one path,
I'll be golden. But if basically the cycle can be reached between these two things,
I could have two simple paths. That's the property. We have the closest vertex on. So
this is the cycle.
There's a cycle here.
If this is the closest vertex to
S and
this is the closest vertex to T on the cycle, then I could take either path
around the cycle to get from one to the other. And that gives me my two paths.
But this path and this path,
these are
completely edge disjoint.
In other words, any simple path from S to T, if I find this vertex going through here,
it can only use one of these edges because I can't come back to this vertex. Once
I go into it here, I got to
go out one direction and I can't come back.
Only one of these two edges. So the idea behind this algorithm is I'm going to find
the cycle, or in particular, I'm going to find this thing S prime on the cycle,
find the outgoing two
edges here,
remove one,
and then do my tree searching. Basically,
find the shortest path by running an
unweighted reachability algorithm, which will give me a path back to S. The only
simple path in that tree. I get rid of this edge. And I do that once. And I do it again
without this edge. So
that's the idea of my algorithm.
So how can I do it? So I first have to find
S prime. How can I do that? Well,
I don't know what this edge is. But if I ran an unweighted shortest
path algorithm, like BFS or DFS on here, I would get back a tree.
Some edge of my graph
will not be in my tree.
Something like here.
The shortest path to this, I look through,
I run B, so algorithm. Idea two.
Two.
First, find
S prime.
And I can find S prime by run,
I don't know,
a single source shortest
path unweighted.
I guess
run
single source reachability unweighted from
S using BFS or DFS
to explore a tree of my graph.
Some edge is not in my tree of the graph. That
will exist on the cycle, kind of by definition.
It's
connecting two parts of my tree.
Now I can
look at those two paths
from here. And the last one that they're in common from S
is going to be my split point, S prime. It's the closest one
to my source
that is on the cycle. Because I constructed
this cycle here.
So I
can find
edge u,
v not in the parent tree. So
maybe this is u, v not in the parent tree.
And then find
last
common vertex
in
paths
from
S to u and S to v.
That's going
to give me my S prime.
And I can do that by, I mean, these are each of linear size. And I can just look at
their prefix. I can start from S. I can walk forward until they diverge. And the one
before they diverge is S prime.
That's S prime right here. Once I have S prime,
I know what the edges are when they diverge.
I remove one of those from the graph. I do the same algorithm again to
find a path to T. And I do the same algorithm again to find the path to T.
And I see which one is shorter. That's it. There's only two of them. And so I check.
Or they could be the same path, in which case my T is actually before S prime on my
cycle. Does that make sense?
So that's the idea. The
last thing is remove an
edge
from S prime. I don't even have to be picky about this. It has degree 3. I
can just run single -sweep -sorted paths on all of them and take them in.
Remove
each edge from S prime.
Remove, let's see, for each
edge from S,
remove
and run SSR from S. OK? And one of the paths there to T will be shortest. My shortest
path in the original graph, because it can't use more than two of those edges.
That's the claim. OK? And this runs in linear time, because
what I'm doing is I'm running single -source reachability
once
and maybe two more times or three
more times, a constant number of times,
on a graph that has size v. And this prefix
finding also only takes order v. And so we're done.
OK?
Any questions about this
problem?
No?
No questions?
All right. We will move on to,
what's up? There's a hint in the title. Yeah. There's a hint in the title. Actually,
the original version of this problem said, instead of this E equals v specification,
it said there's only
one cycle in the graph.
But it's in the context of undirected cycles as opposed to directed cycles, which is
usually what we talk about in this class. We say that there's a negative edge weight
cycle in the graph if we can.
Usually,
we're
allowing non -simple cycles in this class.
So to remember this property about trees and to enforce this property without talking
about cyclicity, I changed the condition for this problem session, this review.
Yeah? Could I also just run depth -first search on this graph? Could you just run
depth -first search on this graph to do what? Well, to find the shortest path. To find
the shortest path,
right? So depth -first search on this path,
if I ran it from S, when I got to S prime, I would
have a choice on what the next outgoing edge to do. OK?
So if I ran depth -first search for one
of those choices, I would find a path to T.
And then I would find a path to T. There's only two of them, or at most two of them.
But then there's the possibility I missed this other path that could be shorter.
Well, how would I miss it if depth -first search has to go through the
other edge, too? It doesn't go through the other edge. That's the point.
It won't go through the dashed edge. It won't go through. No, so depth -first search
will actually go through this thing, traverse an edge, go all the way around the
cycle because everything here is reachable from here because it's an undirected graph.
It will reach back to here and then backtrack all the way. So we'll actually never
traverse
this last edge here of the cycle.
That's something you can actually prove with DFS. Now, you could actually, while
you're running DFS, try every possibility because my branching factor is at most three
at some of these things.
So what I could do is, or it could be at most four. I could connect two things with
the same branching. But in general, it's a constant. And with every choice DFS could
make, I could try all possibilities.
How many possibilities would that be?
So the flow up of the degree
of every vertex in my graph, so the degree
time multiplied by each other. That's the number of
times I would have to run DFS, which is exponential.
A constant degree,
so a constant multiplied like two or three,
multiplied v times. Is three to the v, which
is exponential in the size of my graph. Can I
have that if the size of v equals the size of v?
Sure, right? Because I could still have large
branching for a large number of vertices.
Great question.
All right, cool.
So that's that problem.
Problem three.
I have half an hour for the last
two problems. I think that should be fine.
This one's, OK, this is
Donut is the problem name.
Momar has just finished work at the Fing -Sprield power plant at a particular
location, P, and needs to drive home to a known location, H. But along the way, if his
driving route ever comes
within driving distance, K of a donut shop,
he won't be able to resist himself and will have to go
there and eat donuts. And his wife, Harge, will be angry.
Maybe you can
get the reference here.
Momar knows the layout of Fing -Sprield, which can be modeled as a set of n locations
with two -way roads of known driving distance connecting some pairs of them.
And you may assume that no location is incident to more
than five roads. OK, so we've got a degree bound here.
As well as the location, and he knows, the locations that, all
the locations that contain donut shops. He knows D of them.
OK,
describe an n log n time algorithm to find a shortest driving route from the
power plant back to home that avoids driving within distance K of a donut shop.
OK, so we got a couple variables in here. We've got K,
we've got D, but a running time bound only relies on n.
OK,
I see shortest paths.
I see that,
I don't see an explicit mention of positive distances of the, I see lengths. They say
he knows the known driving distance connecting some pairs of locations. So usually,
I think, if I were writing this problem now, I would probably be a little bit more
explicit that distance is positive. But that's something that you might come into
contact with. Distances are positive. And
so we can't have negative distances here.
So I look at
n log n. I'm like, hey,
what has a log in it in this unit? Dijkstra? Maybe I can use Dijkstra. OK,
so let's see if we ran Dijkstra from P to H. OK, so we've got a graph here.
We've got our graph.
So this is a word problem. So there's no graph there.
So I have to define a graph. So I'm going to define a
graph Ve.
And we've got
V. That's going to be my set of locations.
So
this says there are order
n of them. There's actually n of them.
And then E, what
are we going to have? We're going to have,
it's a known pair of things,
road.
Roads
with
weight equal to driving.
Driving distance, which, by my assumption,
is going to be greater than 0. Now,
that's not stated explicitly, but that would be a reasonable assumption for you to
make on your exam because distances are positive. We would probably be more explicit
about that these days.
All right, so this is
a graph I could make.
I have a vertex P
and a vertex H.
And I'm trying to find the shortest path between
them, shortest driving distance, driving route.
OK, so I could run Dijkstra.
Wait, so what do I know about this? How many edges do I have in my graph?
I have, at most, 5 per vertex. So this is upper bounded by 5 times V,
which is order V. OK, so I have an order
V size graph. That's a good thing. Order n,
because n is the number of vertices. And so
if I were to just run Dijkstra on here from P,
doing Dijkstra
on G from any S takes
order n log n.
n log n plus n.
n log n is bigger than
n. OK, so that's a nice observation.
We can at least afford to use Dijkstra in this problem to find shortest distances.
But what's the problem with a shortest distance found by Dijkstra in this graph?
Donuts, like the entire
point of the problem.
I need to avoid being
too close to donut shops.
I need to avoid a donut shop here. And we need to stay outside of that distance k. Or
we might have another donut shop here. And so we've got to find a path that kind of
goes around these donut shops.
So in other words, if I have a vertex in my graph where I can reach
a donut shop within distance k, I can never visit that vertex.
able to
resist himself and have to go eat a donut.
So that's
the thing we're trying to avoid.
So how can we do this? Well, here's a silly thing. I could run Dijkstra from each
of these vertices, these donut shops, find all the things reachable in k driving
distance from them,
and
then remove those vertices from the graph. That's an idea. But
how long would that take? That would need me to run Dijkstra
d times, because there's d donut shops. I've got to run Dijkstra d times. So that
gives me a running time bound of I run d times to filter out the graph, to modify this
graph. And then I do one more
to find the shortest path if there is one.
But in general, that's going to take d times n log n, not
n log n. I have no bound on d, except that it's under n.
So it could be n, and that would give me about running time.
So we're going to use a very similar trick here to one of your,
I
think, a previous review session.
Stop. Here we go.
When you want to find things, if we want to prune a graph from multiple locations,
one of the things we can do is, any tricks? Supernode, right? I can have a vertex. Oh,
maybe I don't
want to put it up yet.
If I have all of these donut shops, what I can do is provide a, I guess these are
undirected edges. Here, we can model all of those directed things by two undirected
edges. It doesn't really matter. But here, I
don't want to be able to go back to my supernode.
What I can do is I'm going to add a supernode
with edge weight, say, 0 to everything else.
And then if I ran Dijkstra
from the supernode and
found all
vertices reachable within distance k, well,
I didn't spend any of that
distance going through this first edge.
And I didn't come back to s, because these things are directed into the things. And
so anything I reach is going to be within distance k of this donut shop, but for all
donut shops. In some sense, I'm doing this
search in parallel.
So this is the same trick that we had in the, like, you're looking through the sewer
network or something, and they're trying to avoid monitors or sensors or something
like that.
We actually did this transformation and then binary searched on the
distance. It was kind of involved. But this is an easier example.
Now, you can actually generalize
this further. What if each donut shop had
an amount that MoMA liked it?
So if MoMA is within a larger distance of a donut shop
he really likes, he still won't be able to resist.
But a donut shop
that doesn't make very good donuts,
he'll be able to resist a shorter distance without having to go to that donut shop.
So in other words, each one of these donut shops has a different k, a different
radius that MoMA will allow.
Is
there any way to generalize this technique
to be able to prune all
of those vertices instead?
All
of
these had weight 0 before, the same weight.
And would have worked
for any weight I put on all of these edges,
as long as I search
the distance that weight plus k.
Here,
I can just make the distance of this frontier for each one of the
donut shops the same by modifying the distance of the incoming edge.
So I can set the length, the weight, to the
donut shop with the largest radius
to 0. And then put the difference between the largest radius to all the other ones,
I put that as the weight on the other edges. And then we still have a graph with
positive edge weights.
And I can run Dijkstra from this. And that would generalize this problem, and something
that we've done in some practice exams, or in exams and problem sets in the past.
So that's
another common way. So we filter.
Forbidden.
There's
two b's in forbidden, or two d's? Two d's?
There's a three d's.
Vertices
by using
supernode
plus one run of Dijkstra.
Those
are the extra letters. So on your exam, you would probably want to be a little bit
more explicit. This is a summary of the things that we just talked about. I just
talked 10 minutes about
the algorithm.
But it doesn't hurt to add a summary at the top of what you're going to write. This
is the approach that we're going to have. We're going to filter out the vertices from
G,
essentially by running Dijkstra from each of these donut shops.
But we're going to do it in parallel by adding the supernode.
So actually,
another recommendation I have for you on an exam is
that almost any problem that we give you in this class
can get 80 %
to 90 % of the points.
By writing maybe three lines.
Maybe not some of the data structures problems, but almost any question in
this class can be solved with not all of the points, but most of the points
by just writing a couple lines that you know how to solve
the problem. And this would be one of those situations.
Now, I would want to give you four points. I would want all the details here. Did I
construct a new graph? I add this vertex here. I have to add edges to each of the d
things. But I've only added d more edges and one more
vertex. So it still has this linear size in my input.
And then I want to say that I'm putting the weights on here based on what the distance
is. Now, they're all the same weight because I don't have that generalization. And
then I run this thing. And I remove all those graphs. And I construct a new graph
from G. That's a third graph that I'm constructing now. But notice that the graph that
was implicit in my problem was very different than the graph that I'm ultimately
running a shortest path algorithm like Dijkstra from P to C if a path exists. Does that
make sense? Any questions
on this problem?
All right, we've got 20 minutes for my last
problem.
Man, I'm not using it. I write much
less than some of your other instructors.
So I like
to
talk more than I like to write, apparently.
So problem four.
Let's take a look at this. This one's one I
made up last night. Kind of fun.
Long shortest paths. OK, given a directed graph having arbitrary edge weights,
basically these could be positive or negative or 0, and two vertices from the graph,
describe a v cubed time algorithm to find the minimum weight of any path from s to t.
That sounds like Bellman -Ford right there. But I have this last condition. And the
last condition is a little
weird.
So I want a path that
has at least v edges.
So I want a short path
in terms of weight.
But I want a long path, in some sense,
in terms of the number of edges I traverse.
Does that make sense? So of all paths having at least v
edges, I want a shortest one among them in terms of weight.
We're not trying to do this MaxMin kind of thing. We've
got two different quantities here we're trying to optimize.
Anyone have any
ideas on how I could approach this problem?
What does the at least v edges sound similar
to that we might talked about in lecture?
So
when we were talking about Bellman -Ford, we
were defined this thing called a k edge weight.
It's the weight of any path using at most k
edges.
This kind of edge constraint seems similar, except it's kind of
the reverse. It's not at least, it's not at most, it's at least.
Well, here's an observation I have for you. If I
want a path that goes through at least the edges,
some prefix of that path
uses exactly v edges.
Right? That makes sense, right?
So maybe it
makes sense for me to,
maybe it might make this problem easier if it's not at least v edges, but if it's
exactly v edges. Maybe I think about it that way. That seems a reasonable other way to
think about this problem. I knew how to do up to a certain set of edges. Here, we're
asking for at most. Maybe the thing in between is a little easier to think about.
So what we're doing, we're given
a graph,
g, it has any weights.
It's possible
that this graph has e
lower bounded by a quadratic in the vertices. Right? I have no restrictions on how
many edges this thing could be. And so the worst thing I could have is that this
thing, I mean, my graphs are simple. The worst thing I could do is have this be
quadratic in the number of edges, say, if it's the complete graph. That's the maximum
number of edges that I
could have.
And I'm trying to find in my graph
a path that uses a lot of vertices,
but has small weight. Now, what's another thing to notice
here is if I use at least v edges, can my path be simple?
No. Because I need to use at least v plus 1
vertices,
and that's more than the vertices I have in the graph, obviously. Now, it could go
through vertices more than once, but it's definitely not going to be a simple path.
So what's one thing?
What if there's a negative weight cycle in
my graph?
What's the minimum weight of any path from s to t if the negative weight cycle
is reachable on a path from s to t? What is the answer to my problem then?
Negative
infinity, right? Because certainly,
an infinite length path is going to use an
infinite number of edges.
If it's going arbitrarily long, then I can just run Bellman -Ford, right? So that's
one thing I can do. I can just run Bellman -Ford on this graph. I have enough time to
do that, because e is upper bounded
by v squared, and I have v cubed time.
And if there's a negative weight cycle in my graph, I can know that the minimum
weight of any path is minus infinity. I detect that that's the case if, basically,
t is reachable from s with a minimum shortest path distance minus infinity. That the
path that achieves that is going to have more than v edges. So I'm done. And no path
actually achieves that, but
that's the infimum. Supremum. Supremum or infimum. Sorry, we're going lower bound.
I'm thinking of long paths, though. So the number of edges is approaching infinity.
But in the context where I don't have negative weight cycles, actually, one of the
things we showed was that, if you're reachable not through a negative weight cycle, or
if no negative weight cycle is traversable from s
to t, then my shortest path is going to be simple.
But that doesn't seem to apply here, either, because we
need to have a non -simple path. So what do we do? Hmm.
So let's go back to this idea of trying to figure out
the minimum weight of any path using exactly v edges.
Can we use some of the tricks that we had in Bellman -Ford when we're
keeping track of the number of edges we're going through at a given time?
That's the idea.
If we have a vertex,
if we have a new vertex for each vertex, different versions of it that talk about
exactly how many edges I went through, then maybe I could keep track of this while I'm
working on this graph. So let's say I have
multiple layers of the graph. This is the idea.
Maybe we start at level 0 down here to level, how
many edges do I want? I want v plus 1 vertices.
So I'm going to have v plus 1
levels, which is v, right? So a level here,
v, how many levels are there? There's v plus the 0, yeah?
And so I'm going to have, for every edge in my graph,
I'm going to take it.
So this is a directed graph, right? So I
direct it down into the next level. For each
version of this graph
that I have,
I'm going to take that edge that was
originally between u and v here in the graph,
right? It was originally here
in g. But here I've pointed all of
those edges downward,
OK?
Isn't that what we did in Bellman -Ford? We made one other addition in Bellman -Ford
to make it be the at most property, right? What was that transformation we did?
0, 8 edges going from each vertex to another, right?
It meant that we didn't have to traverse an edge,
right? But here, if we don't add those edges, actually, this
transformation gives us that any path that goes through v edges
will be some path from a vertex in layer 0 to a vertex in layer v, right? Just because
to get down here, I had to traverse exactly v edges. And they're the edges of my
original graph.
Now, notice, this encodes
non -simple paths as well, right? Because these things could go, I could go here and
back to u and back to v and back to u if I had a cycle in my graph. But actually,
what kind of graph is this?
This
is a DAG, right? So this is DAG.
Maybe I call this
g prime. How many vertices are in g prime?
v times v plus 1,
right? So I'm going to say order v squared.
And how many
edges are in my graph?
v times e, right? I copied every edge, made it directed down between each level.
There are v transitions between levels. And I copy each edge for each of those. So the
number of edges is order v times
e,
OK? So this graph is blown
up. There's a lot of things in this graph.
But I notice that this graph has size order
v cubed, is what we're going for.
So I
can afford to construct this graph, right?
Actually, also upper
bounded by v squared by simplicity, right?
OK. So we have this graph. We could
find our vertex s here, s0 up here.
And we could afford to compute the shortest path
distance to all other vertices using exactly v edges
in my graph. Exactly. Right? That's what we
could do.
I can find everything reachable from s0 in this graph and calculate the shortest
path down here at the bottom, OK? So I can do that in v cubed time because DAG
relaxation is linear in
the size of the graph.
But that's not what the problem is asking me, unfortunately,
right? In particular, I could find the path to t.
And that would give me the shortest path using
exactly v edges. But that's not what I'm asking for.
I'm asking for
at least.
So it's possible that I get down here to some other
vertex. And maybe there's a negative weight path
going to t. And I want
to be able to find that.
So how can I do that? How can I allow paths
to continue past this? I could have an
arbitrary amount.
I could have more layers, right?
Actually,
simple paths
from any vertex. I mean, shortest paths that are simple, right, that use fewer edges,
right? Here, I'm not restricted on the number of edges I use, right? So shortest
paths in this graph are going to be simple because there's no negative. I can already
throw away the case where I have a negative cycles because I ran Bellman -Ford at
the beginning, right?
So
I know that I'm going
to want a simple path
after I've reached v edges
because it's never going to be beneficial to me to come back to a vertex because that
will be a path of longer weight, right? This is the kind of surgery argument we had
both in unweighted
and weighted context,
OK? So these are going to be simple. So
I know that I only have to go v more layers
at most.
So that's one way to look at it. I could add more layers of this thing,
find the shortest path distance to all vertices using up to 2v edges,
right? Maybe even
2v minus 1, but order v.
And then for all of the ones down below here, I just look
at each vertex and see which weight is the minimum, right?
The way I like to look at it, which is a little bit more fun, I think, is once I'm
down here, I'm just trying to find simple paths in the graph from this vertex v,
right, to this vertex v, right?
So actually, add these,
go up.
So actually, on this bottom layer, right, I want to
find short paths to t from actually every vertex,
right?
And I actually know what the short just from what I did up here, DAG relaxation
on this graph, I knew what the shortest path distance was from s0 to each of these
vertices because I did that in v cubed time up here with DAG relaxation. So I could
add a super node to this thing with a directed edge to each vertex with weighted by
the shortest path
distance I found up above.
Now I have
a graph where any path
from s0 to v
to tv here will be a path that uses at least v edges in my original graph, right?
Because these represent the shortest path weights of anything using exactly v edges.
And then the path
can continue in the original graph,
right?
So now I have a new graph here such that every path from
here to there corresponds to a path that I'm looking for.
So I can find a minimum weight path in this graph. How can
I do that? Now, this graph might have negative weights.
I
can run this with Bellman -Ford.
Bellman
-Ford. I can do that again. Sure, why not?
Now, Jason, why couldn't we just add a bunch of edges here, right? I'll add our
original edges here in the bottom layer of this graph and run Bellman -Ford on this
entire graph.
Why couldn't I do that?
It's too big, right? The number of vertices
is v squared. The number of edges is v,
potentially v cubed. Running Bellman -Ford on that huge duplicated graph would give
me a v to the fifth running time, which is awful, right? In a sense, we're separating
out the complexity. The upper part of the graph has very nice
DAG structure. So let's do shortest paths in that DAG structure
and then reduce
that complexity down.
To just being the thing that has the cycles that we are worried about, reduce the
complexity down here. So how big is this graph? This graph has v plus 1 vertices,
right? Because I only added one super node here. And it has e plus order v edges. I
don't want to be careful here. But this is linear in the size of the original graph.
Bellman -Ford here only
takes v times e time, which is v cubed.
So that's two different ways how to solve this problem. One, using
a bunch of graph duplication and having the insights that going at
most v more steps of this graph duplication
could never get a better thing. So I can stop.
Or recognizing that, well, I have this very powerful algorithm here that can find
shortest paths. Simple paths in a graph without negative weight cycles. And I can use
this super node to transfer
a part of my graph with
a lot of nice structure
down to this other graph.
Any questions about this problem? So these are some, we got two abstract problems for
you, two word problems for you with a lot of different transformations and a lot of
different tricks of your trade.
Any of these, would be something that has either appeared on an
exam or is at a level of something that could appear on your exam.
So go ahead and take a look at the practice material that
we've posted and are accessible from previous year's websites.
And wish you luck
in working on graph problems on your exam.